[band.manual00002.tif]

University of Nebraska
Band Manual

By Charles Ledwith

[band.manual00002.tif]

Library of the University of Nebraska

Gift of

Charles Ledwith (handwritten)

[band.manual00003.tif]

University of Nebraska
BAND MANUAL
Second Edition
Copyright 1937
CHARLES LEDWITH
Drill Instructor
University of Nebraska
R.O.T.C. Bands

(handwritten) Compliments of Charles Ledwith

Boomers Advertising Service
Printing and Mimeographing
Lincoln Nebraska

[band.manual00004.tif]

Dedicated to
William T "Billy" Quick

Since 1918, Director of Bands at the University of Nebraska.
In testimony of the high regard in which is splendid services and genial manner are held by all of us who have worked with him, this manual is inscribed by the author.

402041

[band.manual00005.tif]
UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA
BAND MANUAL

By Charles Ledwith

CONTENTS

FORWARD Page 1.
PART I. THE MILITARY BAND " 2.
Section  Paragraphs
I.  Introduction 1-4. " 2.
II. General Rules and Principles 5-6. " 2.
III.  Commands 7-8. " 3.
IV. Instruction of Bandsman 9-17. " 4.
V.  Steps and Marchings 18-41. " 5.
VI. The Band Officers 42-44. " 12.
VII.  Baton Signals 45-59. " 12.
VIII. Positions of Instruments 60. " 15.
IX. Ceremonies and Inspections 61-62. " 15.
X.  Military Courtesy 63-65. " 16.

PART II. THE FOOTBALL FIELD  " 17.
  "Block" Movements " 17.
  "6 X 16" Formation " 18.
  Sample Football Program " 19.

PART III. MUSIC SUPPLEMENT " 28.

FORWARD

This manual contains excerpts from <u>Drill and Evolution of the Band</u> by Captain Russell B. Reynolds, and <u>Infantry Drill Regulations</u>, which material is also to be found in the training regulations. It is re-printed with permission of the Military Service Publishing Company, owners of the copyrights of the first two publications.

Reference has been made to several training regulations (TR) and army regulations (AR). Any one of these regulations may be obtained by number from the Superintendent of Documents, Government Printing Office, Washington, D. C., by enclosing 5¢ per copy.

The picture of Mr. Quick was sketched by Jean Tool.

1

[band.manual00005.tif]

PART I. THE MILITARY BAND

I.  INTRODUCTION

1. This outline is intended to supplement and to aid in reviewing the basic drill course, and serve as a text for the University of Nebraska R.O.T.C. bands. If the basic course has not been studied, it is even more necessary that this manual be mastered. It consists of an adaptation of infantry drill regulations for use by R.O.T.C. bands and an explanation of the formations of a football band.


2. Nearly every band attempts both to march and to play. Some bands can play well, others can march well; but a few bands can do both. Too great a percentage of rehearsal time spent on either functions seriously impairs the other function. It is therefore important that the drills be planned carefully and that the bandmembers be conversant with the material in this manual so that the purpose of the drill may be accomplished quickly and precisely. Read this manual and re-read it -- even memorize the contents and be able to apply what you learn in drills.

3. Always bear in mind that a greater number of people who hear a band hear it only when it is marching. Indeed, judging from the attendance at concerts compared with the number of football spectators and Parade, the percentage of people who know the band only is a march in group can be estimated at about 90 to 95 per cent. It is evident that the band which would serve to entertain the majority of its audience most perfect all phases of its performance. Marching and playing are equally important to a college band.

4. The purpose of instruction of individuals is to secure smart, precise, uniform movements when the individuals are in formation. The band whose members are well drilled in the basic movements will have a little difficulty, and will consume little time, in mastering the more complex movements of band drill. The tendency is to rush into more advanced drill far too soon. With insufficient elementary instruction, success in drill of the whole band is utterly impossible. Intelligent thorough training in the simple individual movements is an indispensable requirement and should precede any effort at drill of the band as a whole.

II. GENERAL RULES AND PRINCIPLES

5. a. The band may be formed in maneuvered in <u>close order</u>, 4-inch interval between files; in <u>open formation</u>, 9-inch interval between files; and in <u>playing</u> formation, 60–inch interval between files, unless otherwise prescribed. (TR 130-10)

b. The difference the distance between ranks in <u>close order</u> is 40 inches; in <u>open</u> and <u>playing formations</u>, 60 inches.

c. Nebraska R.O.T.C. will seldom use <u>close order</u>.

6. DEFINITIONS. These terms are used in describing movements in the manual:
  Alignment: Straight line upon which several individuals or ele-

2

[band.manual00007.tif]

ments are formed, or are to be formed. The dress of several men on the same line.

Cadence: The rate or number of steps per minute of marching. The rate is established at 128 steps per minute, which is known as quick time.

Distance: Space between elements in the direction of deaths. Distance is measured from the back of the man in front to the best of the man in the rear; distance between bandsmen in formation is two paces (60 inches).

[diagram]

File: Bandsmen arranged in depth. An unoccupied position in a formation is termed a <u>blank file</u>. Thus a file consists of all men having the same number in each rank (A1, B1, C1, and so on, as in figure 2, below), who are arranged one behind the other.

[diagram]

Formation: Arrangement of bandsman in their assigned positions.

Interval: Space between elements or men on the same line. The normal interval between bandsman is two paces (60 inches).

Key-number: When movements are executed in which individuals or groups of men are the units of drill, each man is identified by a distinct letter-number combination corresponding to the alphabetical designation of his rank and the numerical designation of his file in original position in band formation, hereafter called his key-number. It is presented here to facilitate explanation of the text. (See figure 2.)

Rank: Formation in which men are alongside or abreast of each other.

III. COMMANDS.

7. Band drill is executed by oral commands and by baton commands (called baton signals), which commands include two parts; the <u>prepara-</u>

3

[band.manual00008.tif]

<u>tory command</u>, which indicates the movement, such as <u>Forward</u>; and the <u>command of execution</u>, such as <u>MARCH</u>, which starts the execution. There should be a distinct interval between the two parts of commands. It is very important that a drum major time his signals to the fraction of a second, because the band will become accustomed to one way of executing a movement very readily, but will be slow to master a variety of different ways. All movements begin at the command of execution.

8. In this manual preparatory commands are in <u>Capitals and Lowercase, Underlined</u>; commands of execution are in <u>CAPITALS, UNDERLINED</u>. Although a baton signal, accompanied by one or more whistle blasts, will replace most of the verbal commands, it is well, nevertheless, to understand the latter for several reasons. One reason is that all baton signals merely replace verbal commands. Another is that there are situations when verbal commands will be used even although the drum major has his baton and is commanding. The commands covered in section IV have no corresponding baton signals. Most of the commands covered in section V have corresponding baton signals, which are explained and illustrated in section VI.

IV. INSTRUCTION OF THE BANDSMAN, WITHOUT INSTRUMENT

9. Position of Soldier at Attention. Heels on a line, as close together as possible. Feet turned out equally at an angle of 45°. Knees straight without stiffness. Hips level and drawn back slightly. Body erect and resting equally on hips. Chest lifted and arched. Shoulders square and falling equally. Arms hanging straight back down without stiffness. Thumbs along seams of trousers. Backs of hands out. Fingers are curled naturally. Head erect and square to front. Chin drawn in so the axis of neck and head is vertical. Eyes straight to front. Weight of body resting equally on heels in both feet. The heels are brought together smartly and audibly. The <u>mind</u> as well as the <u>body</u> must be out of tension. (When instruments are carried, maintain this position except as modified by the carrying of the instrument.)

10. The Rests. Being at a halt, the commands are: <u>FALL OUT</u>; <u>AT EASE</u>; 1. <u>Stand at</u>, 2. <u>EASE</u>; or 1. <u>Parade</u>, 2. <u>REST</u>.

11. At <u>FALL OUT</u>, the men may leave ranks, but must remain in the vicinity. They resume their positions at <u>Attention</u> at the command <u>FALL IN</u>.

12. At <u>REST</u>, each man keeps his right foot in place, but is not required to preserve silence or immobility. He may talk, move, etc.

13. <u>AT EASE</u> is the same as rest, except that silence is preserved. At 1. <u>Stand at</u>, 2. <u>EASE</u>, at the command of execution, move the left foot smartly 12 inches to the left of the right foot, and at the same time clasp hands behind the back, palms to the rear, thumb and fingers of the right hand clasp in the left thumb. Preserve silence and immobility. (Never used in band formation.)

4

[band.manual00009.tif]

14. At 1. <u>Parade</u>, 2. <u>REST</u>, carry the right foot 6 inches straight to the rear and bend left knee slightly, weight of body resting equally on both feet. At the same time, clasp hands in front of center of body, left hand outermost, fingers straight, left thumb clasped by right hand. Preserve silence and immobility. (There is no occasion when the band executed this movement as a unit. However, it is well to understand this movement as it will be commanded in a review, parade, etc., immediately before the command <u>SOUND OFF</u>.)

15. Being in any position of rest, at the command: 1. <u>Band</u>, 2. <u>ATTENTION</u>, snap smartly to Attention at the command of execution.

16. Movements or facings that are executed similarly toward both flanks are explained in this manual as for one flank. To adapt the movement to the other flank, substitute <u>Left</u> or <u>Right</u> as required. Such movements are indicated by the word left or right in parentheses in the command.

17. Facings. All facings are executed in the cadence of quick time. To face to the flank the command is: 1. <u>Right</u> (<u>Left</u>), 2. <u>FACE</u>. At the command FACE, raise slightly the left heel and right toe and turn 90° to the right on the right heel, assisted by pressure of the ball of the left foot. (TWO) Place the left foot smartly beside the right. Left Face is similarly executed on the left heel. No part of the body should move except the left (right) leg. 1. <u>Right (Left) half</u>, 2. <u>FACE</u>, is executed similarly, turning 45° instead of 90°.

To face to the rear the command is: 1. <u>About</u>, 2. <u>FACE</u>. Carry the toe of the right foot about a half foot-length to the rear and 3 inches to the left of the left heel, weight of body being chiefly on the left heel, right leg straight. 2. Face to the rear, turning to the right on the left heel and ball of right foot, place the right heel beside the left. Practice this out of rank until you learn exactly where to place your right toe.

V. STEPS AND MARCHINGS.

18. All steps in marching executed from a halt (except <u>Right step</u>) begin with the left foot. In quick time the length of a full step (heel to heel) is 30 inches and the cadence is 128 steps per minute. Double time is rarely used in band.

19. For movements executed towards the right (left), while in march, the command of execution is given as the right (left) foot strikes the ground. Advance and plant the other foot – that is, take one full step – and then execute the movement.

20. Any movement may be executed either from a halt or while marching, unless otherwise prescribed.

21. Partial changes in direction are ordered by adding the word "half" to the preparatory command, as: <u>Column half right</u>. The change

5

[band.manual00010.tif]

PART I, Sec. V.  STEPS AND MARCHINGS

Of direction is 45° instead of 90°. Slight changes are executed at the command: <u>INCLINE TO THE RIGHT (LEFT)</u>.

22. Correction of Commands. To arrest a movement for any purpose, the command is: 1. <u>In Place</u>, 2. <u>HALT</u>, All halt. To resume the movement, the command is: 1. <u>Resume</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. To retract a preparatory command for any reason, the command is: <u>AS YOU WERE</u>. The movement is not executed unless both preparatory in command of execution are given anew.

23. To March Forward: Being at a halt, half step, or marking time, the command is: 1. <u>Forward</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. If at a halt, at the preparatory command, shift the weight to the right foot without perceptible movement. At the command march, take a full step (30 inches) forward with the left foot. Continue to march, allowing the arms to swim naturally, but not excessively (9 inches in all – six ahead, three behind).

24. To Halt. Being in march or marking time, command is: 1. <u>Band</u>, 2. <u>HALT</u>. At the command <u>HALT</u>, usually given as the left foot strikes the ground for band, but properly given as either foot strikes the ground, advance and point the other foot – that is, take one more full step – then bring the rear foot up and plant it on the line with the other. In marking time or marching backwards, the procedure is similar. That is, take one more step in cadence and then halt.

25. Half Step. The command is: 1. <u>Half step</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. Half step is executed exactly the same manner as full step, except that the length of the step is 15 inches. To resume full step, the command is: 1. <u>Forward</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>.

26. Side Step. Being at a halt or marking time, the command is: 1. <u>Right (Left) Step</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. At the command <u>MARCH</u>, move and plant the right (left) foot ten inches to the right (left), and bring the other foot alongside. Continue in the cadence of quick time. In haultingfrom side step, the command <u>HALT</u> should be given as the feet come together. Then take one step to the side and complete the heart as the feet again come together.

27. Back Step. Being at a halt or marking time, the command is: 1. <u>Backward</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. Backward march is executed in exactly the same manner as forward march, except the length of step is 15 inches and the direction is opposite. The halt is made in the same way. The movement is used for short distances only.

28. Being at a halt, to face to the right (left) in marching and advance: At the command of execution, turn in the designated direction on the ball of the <u>right</u> foot and at the same time step off in the new direction with the left foot, taking a full 30-inch step.

29. Being in march, to face to the right (left) in marching in advance: At the command of execution, given as the right (left) foot

6

[band.manual00011.tif]

PART I, Sec. V  STEPS AND MARCHINGS

strikes the ground, advance and plant the left (right) foot. To turn to the right (left) on the ball of the left (right) foot, and at the same time step off in the new direction with the right (left) foot in a full or half step.

30. To March by the Flank. Being in march, the command is: 1. <u>By the Right (Left) Flank</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. At the command <u>MARCH</u>, given as the right (left) foot strikes the ground, advance and plant the left (right) foot, face the right (left) in marching on the ball of the left (right) foot, and step off in the new direction with the right (left) foot with a full 30-inch step.

TO CHANGE THE DIRECTION OF MARCH.

31. Regulation Style (see figure 3). The command is: 1. <u>Column Right (Left)</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. At the command of execution, given for column right as the right foot strikes the ground, for column left as the left foot strikes the ground, all but the leading rank take up half step. The right- (left-) flank pivot man of the leading rank faces to

[ figure ] Figure 3.

At the command of execution, all take up half step to turning point.

Pivot man face in marching, take one full step in new direction.

Others oblique at full step. Take up half step when abreast pivot man.

This figure shows movement after 24 counts.

Shaded circles represent men at half step.

7

[band.manual00012.tif]

PART I, Sec. V  STEPS AND MARCHINGS

the right (left) in marching, takes one full step to clear the way for the pivot man of the rank just in the rear, and then marches in the new direction at half step. All other men execute smart, precise right oblique until they are on the line with the original pivot file; they then execute the second right oblique, march up abreast of the pivot man and take up the half step. All succeeding ranks execute the movement on the same ground and in the same manner. Resume full step at the command Forward March.

Turning movements are the most difficult of band drill in which to secure precision and smartness of execution. There is a tendency for the turning point to wander from where it was first established by the leading rank. It is common for those marching at half step to take a step longer than 15 inches. Too short a step is almost as bad. Familiarity with the facings in marching (paragraphs 28 and 29), the oblique march (paragraph 35), and the half step (paragraph 25) are central to the execution of this movement.

32. The Modified "Wheel" Turn (see figure 4). The command is the same as for the regulation style. At the command of execution, the front rank describes an arc of 90° to the right (left), with the pivot moving immediately in the new direction at a quarter step, and the left- (right-) flank man marching at a full step. Guide is in both directions during the arc, with the interval taken from the moving pivot, which causes the arc to deflect slightly to the right (left).

Figure 4.

THE MODIFIED "WHEEL" TURN Partially completed.

(Every other rank in shaded circles.)

8

[band.manual00013.tif]

PART I, Sec. V STEPS AND MARCHINGS

When the entire rank is turned in the new direction, it proceeds at a half step. The remainder of the band takes up the half step at the command of execution. All succeeding ranks execute the movement on the same ground and in the same manner. The pivot men will retain the regular distance from the rank in front until they have turned in the new direction, when they will immediately decrease it to half the regular distance; the correct distance will be regained as each rank completes the term. When the entire band is turned, it moves forward at a full step at the drum majors command.

Note. See page 17 for another style of turn.

REVERSING THE DIRECTION OF MARCH.

33. The Military Countermarch (see figure 5). The band being in playing formation (see figure 5), to countermarch, the command is: 1. <u>Countermarch</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. At the command of execution, given as either foot strikes the ground, all take up the half step. The files to the right of the middle of the band (including the center file) turn to the right about; the files to the left of the middle turn left about; each man marching on the circumference of a circle 30 inches in diameter. Each rank executes the same movement successively, and on the same ground. A separation will be caused in the middle of the band, which will be adjusted by an oblique to the center of each rank as it emerges from the rear of the band, the last rank closing in as soon as the turn is completed. The half step is continued until Forward March is commanded by the drum major as the last rank completes the turn. The movement can be executed at full step; but it is not advisable to do so because of the interference in passing between files, especially since this movement is always executed while playing.

[Figure 5.]

(Shaded circles are men who have not executed movement.)

34. The Irreversible Countermarch (see figure 6). To reverse the direction of march without altering the order in which the band is arranged from side to side (so that the right side of the band before countermarching will remain at the right side of the completion of the movement), the command is the same for the military coun-

9

[band.manual00014.tif]

PART I, Sec. V STEPS AND MARCHINGS

[Figure 6.]

(Odd-numbered files shown by shaded circles.)

(Dotted lines show paths to be followed.)

(Paragraphs 34, continued.) termarch described in paragraph 33. At the command of execution, the leading man at the center file or first file to the left of the middle, turns to his right about, marching on the circumference of a circle 30 inches in diameter. The leading man of the file on his right marches to the left about on the circumference of a circle 90 inches in diameter. The leading man of the file to the left of the first file marches to his right about on a circle 150 inches in diameter. Alternating in the above matter, each file marches around a larger circle. The movement is executed at full step until the last man in the file having the least distance to travel has completed his turn. At this moment the drum major commands half step by the baton signal for Correct Alignment. When the file having the greatest distance to travel is even with the others at half step commands: Forward March. All step off at full step.

Note. See page 18 for a third style of countermarch.

35. The Oblique March (see figure 7). Being at a halt or marching, the command is: 1. <u>Right (Left) Oblique</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. Each man faces half right (left) in marching at the command of execution, and steps off in the new direction. The ranks remain parallel to the original front and the files remain at right angles to the ranks.

36. At the command <u>HALT</u>, given as the left foot strikes the ground in halting from Right Oblique, or as the right foot strikes the ground in halting from Left Oblique, advance and please plant the right (left) foot in the direction of the oblique, turn to the original front on the ball of the right (left) foot, and place the other foot alongside. Thus, on halting, the unit is faced to the original front.

10

[band.manual00015.tif]

PART I, Sec. V STEPS AND MARCHINGS

[Figure 7]

37. To resume the original direction without halting, the command is: 1. <u>Forward</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. Each man faces half left in marching and continues in the original direction. If at a half step or mark time while obliquing, the oblique march is resumed at the command: 1. <u>Oblique</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>.

38. To Augment the Interval Between Files (see figure 8). Being in march in open formation (para. 5), the command is: 1. <u>Increase Front</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. at the command <u>MARCH</u>, if the number of files is even, the entire file immediately to the right (left) of the middle of the band takes one step to the right (left) oblique; the next file to the right (left) takes three steps tot he right (left) oblique; and so on, each succeeding file taking two more steps to the right (left) oblique than the file next to it nearer the middle. the inside files will take up the half step upon completing the oblique, stepping off with a full step without signal.

[ Figure 8 ]

11
402041

[band.manual00016.tif]

PART I, Sec. VII BATON SIGNALS

39. To Diminish the Interval Between Files. The command is: 1. <u>Decrease Front</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. The movement is executed in a manner similar to Increase Front, the files obliquing a like number of steps towards the middle of the band, instead of away from the middle.

40. CAUTION. In the movements described above, the command of execution must be given at exactly the right time, as a particular foot strikes the ground in most cases. If this command is given between steps, or on the wrong foot, a ragged execution of the movement must result. Practice all of these movements out of ranks until you were able to execute each movement perfectly in any position in the band. Good drill is impossible unless every man correctly executes the fundamental movements.

41. Route Marches. The commands are: 1. <u>Route Step</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>; or: 1. <u>At Ease</u>, 2. <u>MARCH</u>. Regulations require the instruments be carried at the prescribed <u>carry</u> positions. In R.O.T.C. band, this is not to be insisted upon. And neither of the Route Marches are the men required to keep step, but if marching At Ease, silence must be maintained. If halted while at Route Step, the band is At Rest; if halted while marching At Ease, the band is At Ease. To reestablish cadence, bringing the band to Attention, the command is: 1. <u>Band</u>, 2. <u>ATTENTION</u>. Drums commence to beat on the next count. Others take the cadence from teh drums.

VI. BAND OFFICERS

42. The drum major is in charge of the band while in formation, commanding it and directing its playing by means of verbal commands and signals of the drum major's baton, in the manipulation of which he must be an expert. For the R.O.T.C. bands, drum majors will be selected on the basis of skills with the baton, force of command, stature, and appearance.

43. The band captain and his lieutenants assist the instructor in charge to maintain discipline and instruct the band. These duties attach to the officers whether in rehearsal or a drill. In addition, the officers will be in charge of social functions and the promotion of other activities of the band.

44. When in formation, the drum major and field officers only salute for the entire band with saluting is prescribed in AR 600-25. The drum major and officers will be held to a knowledge of the applicable regulations, which they will apply by hand or baton salute.

VII. BATON SIGNALS.

45. The baton is carried by the drum major whenever instruments are carried by the band. (See Manual of the Baton in TR 130-10.)

46. Baton signals are given from three positions, with which the band must be familiar, namely: a. <u>Order baton</u>, b. <u>Carry baton</u>, and

12

