<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="band.doc.0001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Petition for the Formation of a University Concert Band</title>
<title type="sub"/>
<principal n="Dussault, Jessica" xml:id="jvd">Jessica Dussault</principal>
<principal n="Robison, Traci" xml:id="tr">Traci Robison</principal>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>Cornhusker Marching Band History</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">band.doc.0001</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title type="m">Petition for the Formation of a University Concert Band</title>
<date when="1922-01">January 1922</date>
<author/>
<note type="project"/>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>University of Nebraska-Lincoln Archives and Special Collections</repository>
<collection>RG 051001 Samuel Avery, Correspondence, Chancellor Records</collection>
<idno>Box 1, Folder 5</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence &amp; Papers</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Quick, W. T.</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Concert</term>
<term>Fundraising &amp; Finance</term>
<term>Military</term>
<term>Other Band</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020" who="#jvd">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="document">
<pb facs="0000"/>
<opener> Chancellor Avery,<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>

<p>We, the undersigned, wish to establish an advanced University Concert Band at the University of Nebraska upon the following plans and recommendations with your approbation:</p>

<p>I. The new band to be independent of the Military Department or R.O.T.C.</p>

<p>Due to the Army Reorganization Bill recently passed by Congress, Upperclassmen registering for the Cadet Band are not to be issued uniforms and other equipment. This bill calls for an appropriation of $30.00 for each cadet for two years time only. No provision is made for upperclassmen. Either the upperclassmen must pay for their own uniform, the University pay for it, or the upperclassmen must register again as Freshman in the band. None of these methods, it is easily seen, are satisfactory. Upperclassmen will not register again as freshmen, nor will they buy their own military uniform. The only reason why upperclassmen, who have completed their drill requirements, are now registered under the R.O.T.C. department, is because they wish to add their very much needed talent to Nebraska’s only band.</p>

<p>Nebraska should have an advanced band to take care of these upperclassmen and also for eligible underclassmen Such a band should be independent of the Military Department and placed on the same status as the University Orchestra. This is desirable for several reasons other than that mentioned above. In the first place, there has been considerable friction between the upperclassmen of the band and the Military Department over matters of drill and military supervision. A band should be the last organization to be affected by friction and hard feeling towards its supervisors. In the second place, the present band is too large for the best musical development of its members. Musicians coming in as freshman are required, regardless of ability, to take the low positions in their section for two to three years before advancing into the solo chairs. This is due to the presence of the upperclassmen in these solo positions. Freshmen thus become discouraged and drop out after their drill requirements are made.</p>

<p>The formation of a new concert band for advanced students is highly desirable then, because of the need for an outlet for the upperclassmen so as to provide advancement for the underclassmen, and because the new Army Reorganization Bill makes it practically impossible for upperclassmen to be in the present Cadet Band.</p>

<pb facs="0000"/>

<p>II. This new concert band will be based entirely upon merit. It will be an advanced course in band for advanced students in music. The Cadet Band will act as a preliminary training band, the most conscientious players of which will be eligible for the advanced band. Nebraska needs such a band and has needed it for some time. Due to the absence of it, Nebraska has been deprived of much excellent talent because many players will not be in the Cadet Band under military supervision.</p>

<p>III. That the new band shall be known as the University Concert Band. It shall be the official band of the University on every occasion, and entitled to all the privileges and practices now enjoyed by the Cadet Band, such as Football trips, Spring trips, and other University functions or public appearance non-military in nature.</p>

<p>IV. The University Concert Band will pledge itself to work to the best interests of the University by its hearty participation in college affairs. It would like to put on several convocations throughout the Winter and Spring, and also a public concert for the people of Lincoln to hear. It would like to be better known to the students and people of Lincoln as a concert band rather than as a “ballyhoo” or military march band. Its utmost efforts and purpose will be toward better music, musicians and a better University. Every member of the new band will be a member of the national band fraternity, Gamma Lambda, whose purpose is for better ideals in music in college bands. At Nebraska is located the Alpha chapter of this fraternity. Nebraska must set a high example to other college bands. The new University Concert Band will give Nebraska that opportunity.</p>

<p>V. Uniforms of the band to be something on the order of those of the University Corncobs; i.e. Scarlet and cream cap, scarlet sweater, and cream trowsers. Uniforms to be paid for by the members themselves.</p>

<p>VI. One hour credit be allowed for three hours practice, as is the case at present.</p>

<p>VII. Music for the Band to be covered by a nominal fee upon registration, or purchased by the band itself as occasion arises, preferably the latter.</p>

<p>VIII. That Mr. W.T. Quick, Director of the Cadet Band, be assigned to the Concert Band as director. At present there is no School of Agriculture Band, and Mr. Quick expresses his willingness to direct this new band in its place. As for ourselves, we would like to see the School of Agriculture Band discontinued permanently at least as far as Mr. Quick’s services are required, and such services by him be assigned to the new band. This would relieve the necessity of increasing the Director’s salary.</p>

<p>Petition 3 of 5</p>

<pb facs="0000"/>

<p>IX. As evidence of the feasibility of this plan, we cite the case of the University of Illinois Concert Band. This band, founded upon principles
identical with these outline in this petition, and organized as a result of the same difficulties which now confront us, has gained national recognition as the greatest college band in the country. We believe ours to be a parallel case.</p>

<p>The lists of signers are on the following pages.</p>

<p>LISTS OF SIGNERS</p>

<p>I. Upperclassmen now in the Cadet Band who desire to form the Concert Band, and express their intention of dropping the Cadet Band at the end of this semester under present conditions:</p>
<list rend="simple">
<item>Lester H. Boyd</item>
<!-- Howard J. Heim -->
<item>H. J. Heim</item>
<item>Leroy D. Clements</item>
<item>Francis J. Wells</item>
<!-- Remey L. Clem -->
<item>R. L. Clem</item>
<!-- Clark W. Adams -->
<item>C. W. Adams</item>
<!-- Everett Wyman -->
<item>E. A. Wyman</item>
<item>James C. Wilson</item>
<item>William T. Novak</item>
<item>Wayne T. Gray</item>
<!-- Warren E. Sturtevant -->
<item>W. T. Sturtevant</item>
<!-- Harry Stevens -->
<item>H. E. Stevens</item>
<!-- Wilber O. Johnson -->
<item>W. O. Johnson</item>
<item>M. E. Bonth</item>
<!-- Harvey A. Seaman -->
<item>H. A. Seaman</item>
<!-- Denver D. Roos -->
<item>D. D. Roos</item>
<item>Edward C. Fisher</item>
<item>Paul C. Coglizer</item>
<item>Claude C. Ryan</item>
<item>W. C. Lowe</item>
<item>Burford B. Gage</item>
<item>Vernon A. Forbes</item>
<!-- Gorden N. Watkins -->
<item>G. N. Watkins</item>
</list>

<pb facs="0000"></pb>

<p>II. Former Band men and other eligible musicians who will register for the Concert Band:</p>
<list rend="simple">
<item>Oscar H. Gregoake</item>
<item>Rudolph <unclear>C</unclear></item>
<item>Jaro <unclear>M</unclear></item>
<item>Emmett S. Sanders</item>
<item>Cecil I. Mathews</item>
<item>Amos Ginn</item>
<item>Merwin Johnson</item>
</list>

<p>III. Underclassmen eligible for the new Band now in Cadet Band:</p>
<list rend="simple">
<item>John V. Anderson</item>
<item>Clement E. Ragan</item>
<item>Audley N. Sullivan</item>
<item>Irwin Wilkes</item>
<item>Drew Bickford</item>
<!-- Floyd L. Ammer -->
<item>Floyd Ammer</item>
<item>Burton Warrick</item>
<item>Norman L. Cramb</item>
<item>Raymond L. Smith</item>
<item>Maurice F. Schickley</item>
<!-- Theodore E. Barger -->
<item>Ted Barger</item>
<item>Sam F. Seeley</item>
</list>

<p>IV. We, the undersigned, affix our signatures as representatives of the student body, knowing that it is behind this movement:</p>
<list rend="simple">
<!-- Hugh M. Carson -->
<item>H. M. Carson, President, Innocents</item>
<item>G. H. Smith, Cap’t Basketball Team</item>
<!-- Glen O. Munger -->
<item>G. O. Munger President Student Council</item>
<item>Clarence Swanson, Cap’t 1921 Football Team</item>
<item>Margaret Henderson, President Mortorboard</item>
<item>Leonard M. Cowley, Representative of Daily Nebraskan</item>
<item>Ruth Fickes, President of W.A.A.</item>
</list>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
